<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Quick Start Guide on UGENE Quick Start Guide</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/</link><description>Recent content in Quick Start Guide on UGENE Quick Start Guide</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>View, Edit and Annotate DNA, RNA, and Protein Sequences</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/view-edit-and-annotate-dna-rna-and-protein-sequences/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/view-edit-and-annotate-dna-rna-and-protein-sequences/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="view-edit-and-annotate-dna-rna-and-protein-sequences">View, Edit, and Annotate DNA, RNA, and Protein Sequences&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DNA, RNA, or protein sequences (&lt;em>Sequence View&lt;/em>).&lt;/strong> The &lt;em>Sequence View&lt;/em> is one of the major object views in UGENE
designed to visualize and edit DNA, RNA, or protein sequences along with their properties like annotations,
chromatograms, 3D models, statistical data, etc. For each file, UGENE analyzes the file content and automatically opens
the most appropriate view. To activate the &lt;em>Sequence View&lt;/em>, open any file with at least one sequence. For example, you
can use the $&lt;em>ugene/data/samples/Genbank/murine.gb&lt;/em> file provided with UGENE. After opening the file in UGENE, the
&lt;em>Sequence View&lt;/em> window appears:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>What is UGENE?</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-is-ugene/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-is-ugene/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="what-is-ugene">What is UGENE?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>Unipro UGENE&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> is a free cross-platform genome analysis suite. It is distributed under the terms of the GNU General
Public License. To learn more about UGENE, visit the &lt;a href="http://ugene.unipro.ru">UGENE website&lt;/a>. It works on Windows, Mac
OS X, or Linux and requires only a few clicks to install.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="key-features">Key Features&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Powerful viewers and editors for DNA and protein sequences, multiple sequence alignments, chromatograms,
3D-structures, short read assemblies, and phylogenetic trees.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Support for dozens of data formats, and a set of tools for importing and exporting data.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Visual designer, runner, and debugger for computational workflows from over 100 embedded algorithmic elements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reusable computational workflows that can be shared, published, and read as plain text by everyone.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A fully featured command-line version for remote desktops.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Automatic detection and optimization for multicore hardware, GPGPU, and special instruction sets available on the
user&amp;rsquo;s PC.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Setting up the UGENE package automatically gets dozens of tools installed and configured for immediate use.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="tools-provided-with-ugene-installation">Tools provided with UGENE installation&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>BLAST - a popular tool for searching similarities between biological sequences.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>HMMER2/HMMER3 - sequence analysis using profile hidden Markov models, constructed from multiple sequence alignments.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ClustalW, ClustalO, MUSCLE, Kalign, MAFFT, T-Coffee multiple sequence alignment algorithms.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Repeat finding and sequence comparison algorithms with convenient dot-plot-based results visualization.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Open reading frames visualization and export.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Restriction sites visualization tool with the integrated REBASE database.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transcription factor binding sites analysis with SITECON, weight-matrix-based algorithms, and included versions of the
JASPAR database.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Short read aligners: BWA, BWA-MEM, Bowtie, Bowtie2, TopHat, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>GC-content, AT-content graphs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>MrBayes, Phylip, and PhyML tools for phylogenetic tree construction.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;hellip; and dozens of other popular and highly cited tools.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="commercial-support">Commercial support&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The commercial support includes bug-fixing on a priority basis, implementation of new features, and more. To learn more,
please &lt;a href="mailto:ugene@unipro.ru">contact us&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>View, Edit and Align Multiple Sequence Alignments</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/view-edit-and-align-multiple-sequence-alignments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/view-edit-and-align-multiple-sequence-alignments/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="view-edit-and-align-multiple-sequence-alignments">View, Edit and Align Multiple Sequence Alignments&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Multiple Sequence Alignment (&lt;em>MSA Editor&lt;/em>).&lt;/strong> The &lt;em>Alignment Editor&lt;/em> is a powerful tool for visualizing and editing
DNA, RNA, or protein multiple sequence alignments. To activate the &lt;em>Alignment Editor&lt;/em> open any alignment file. For
example, you can use the $&lt;em>ugene/data/samples/CLUSTALW/COI.aln&lt;/em> file provided with UGENE. After opening the file in
UGENE, the &lt;em>Alignment Editor&lt;/em> window appears:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/images/2883700/3080199.gif" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The editor supports different multiple sequence alignment (MSA) formats, such as ClustalW, MSF, and Stockholm. The
editor provides an interactive visual representation which includes:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>View, Align and Assemble Short Reads</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/view-align-and-assemble-short-reads/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/view-align-and-assemble-short-reads/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="view-align-and-assemble-short-reads">View, Align and Assemble Short Reads&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>SAM/BAM Files (&lt;em>Assembly Browser&lt;/em>).&lt;/strong> The &lt;em>Assembly Browser&lt;/em> is used to visualize and efficiently browse large
next-generation sequence assemblies. Currently, supported formats are SAM (Sequence Alignment/Map) and BAM, which is a
binary version of the SAM format. Both formats are produced by SAMtools and are described in the following
specification: SAMtools. To activate the &lt;em>Alignment Editor&lt;/em>, open any assembly file. For example, you can use the $
&lt;em>ugene/data/samples/Assembly/chrM.bam&lt;/em> file provided with UGENE. After opening the file in UGENE, the &lt;em>Assembly Browser&lt;/em>
window appears:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D Structures and Surface Algorithms</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/3d-structures-and-surface-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/3d-structures-and-surface-algorithms/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="3d-structures-and-surface-algorithms">3D Structures and Surface Algorithms&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>3D Structures (&lt;em>3D Structure Viewer&lt;/em>).&lt;/strong> The &lt;em>3D Structure Viewer&lt;/em> is designed for the visualization of 3D structures
of biological molecules. Using the &lt;em>3D Structure Viewer&lt;/em>, you can work with data from the Protein Data Bank (PDB), a
repository for the 3D structural data of large biological molecules, such as proteins and nucleic acids, maintained by
the Worldwide Protein Data Bank (wwPDB). You can also work with data from the NCBI Molecular Modeling Database (MMDB),
also known as &amp;ldquo;Entrez Structure,&amp;rdquo; a database of experimentally determined structures obtained from the RCSB Protein Data
Bank.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Workflow Designer: Pipelines and Repeatable Experiments</title><link>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/workflow-designer-pipelines-and-repeatable-experiments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ugene.net/quick-start-guide/what-you-can-do-in-ugene/workflow-designer-pipelines-and-repeatable-experiments/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="workflow-designer-pipelines-and-repeatable-experiments">Workflow Designer: Pipelines and Repeatable Experiments&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Workflow Designer.&lt;/strong> UGENE &lt;em>Workflow Designer&lt;/em> is a central part of &lt;a href="http://ugene.unipro.ru/">UGENE&lt;/a> that allows a
molecular biologist to create and run complex computational workflows, even if they are not familiar with any
programming language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A workflow comprises a reproducible, reusable, and self-documented research routine, with a simple and unambiguous
visual representation suitable for publications. A workflow can be run both locally and remotely, either using a
graphical interface or launched from the command line. Elements in the workflow correspond to algorithms integrated
into &lt;a href="http://ugene.unipro.ru/">UGENE&lt;/a>. Additionally, you can create custom workflow elements using an integrated
scripting language or by connecting arbitrary external command line utilities.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>